Guide to the John Ruskin Letters to Ellen Heaton
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Letters from John Ruskin to Ellen Heaton, Ruskin, John, 1819-1900
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 October?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 11 cm (Box 1, Folder H.17)
    Ruskin thanks Heaton for plums she sent to his family. Ruskin praises examples of Heaton's writing she had sent to him but admits that he has only been able to read one piece. Ruskin advises that "[Heaton] may make it funnier & more useful by making it shorter" and that she "would write very nice & useful things in a little while but [she] want[s] a little training.". Ruskin asks if he can keep the articles until Christmas, to give him time to read them properly. [Date provided by Surtees: ? October 1855; letter marked "Friday morning"]
    Rhetoric; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 November 8; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 2 sheets, 1 folded (6 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm and 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.18)
    Ruskin comments on a variety of Rossetti works which Heaton might wish to purchase. He complains about Rossetti's penchant for throwing away his works or altering them so much that they develop "odd faults." Ruskin tells Heaton that although Rossetti's The Passover in the Holy Family was intended for him, Ruskin had planned to "give it up" for Heaton, that was until Rossetti altered it, and increased its price. Ruskin tells Heaton that Rossetti has begun a drawing for her but that it is "a most gloomy drawing - very grand - but dreadful.". He remarks that, if Heaton refuses the piece, Rossetti "may get into a bad humour" but states that "prudish people might perhaps think it not quite a young lady's drawing." Ruskin advises Heaton to inform him of her purchasing intentions as soon as possible and asks her to forgive him for keeping The Passover.
    Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Passover in the Holy Family; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Beatrice meeting Dante at a marriage feast, denies him her salutation; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 November 9?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.19)
    Ruskin tells Heaton that if he sends her any Rossetti works they must not be described as belonging to him. Ruskin explains he has not been able to answer her letters as he is still unwell. Ruskin informs Heaton he managed to purchase for her two prints from Turner's Liber Studiorium compositions, although he states that these are not "good" and that he will also send her another two, which are. Ruskin approves of Heaton's plans for a Rossetti exhibition and offers his assistance. He ends by admitting: "I don't know if you can read this -- I am'nt [sic] going to try myself." [Date provided by Surtees: ? November 9th 1855]
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Liber Studiorum; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 November 12?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.21)
    Ruskin tells Heaton he has sent her the Rossetti works which he suggests she look at extensively but that she should "keep them locked up -- lest the one should be laughed at for its errors." He remarks that Rossetti's Francesca di Rimini is a "bold -- but perfectly true reading of Dante.". He tells Heaton that he is going to make Rossetti redo Guinevere & Lancelot "without mistakes" and that he will keep "the best of the two" and let Heaton have the other. Ruskin explains that Turner's Parnassus depicts a scene in the afternoon, not at noon and, in a postscript, remarks that the work's "immediate foreground shadows" are "indefensible ... [Turner] was very careless about scientific matters." [Date provided by Surtees: ? November 12th 1855]
    Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Arthur's Tomb; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Paolo and Francesca da Rimini; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Parnassus and Castalian Spring; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 mid-November?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.22)
    Ruskin apologizes for not having previously written to Heaton about Rossetti's Paolo and Francesca and tells her if she likes his Rossetti better, he will make an exchange with her as "both are exquisite examples of him." Ruskin tells her that he now has more free time, having finished his draft of what will become Modern Painters III, and that he shall read Heaton's writings. In a postscript, he admits that he doesn't care which Rossetti painting he has as he admires them both. [Date provided by Surtees: Probably mid-November 1855]
    Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Paolo and Francesca da Rimini; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900. Modern painters; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 mid-November?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.23)
    Ruskin tells Heaton he will send her requested photographs alongside the bill for them. He remarks that Rossetti's Rachel shows the dangers of commissioning specific scenes for the artist as "he never would fail in a subject of his own choice.". He thinks that Rachel's face is very beautiful and is "spoiled only by [sic] small underlip." He tells Heaton that it is a portrait of Elizabeth Siddall. He praises the work's use of colour. Ruskin asks Heaton if she has a copy of his "PreRaphaelitism" pamphlet which gives an account of Turner's destroyed Brignall Church. Ruskin tells Heaton that while the Arthur Hughes's painting is "very beautiful" she would do better to become a patron of Rossetti's work. [Date provided by Surtees: Probably mid-November 1855]
    Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's vision of Rachel and Leah; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Brignall Church; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Siddall, Elizabeth; Hughes, Arthur, 1832-1915; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 late November; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.24)
    Ruskin admits that he had not written about Heaton's latest commission for Rossetti as he assumed she would know he was pleased by it. He tells Heaton to keep both Rossettis as long as she likes. He tells her to send him the money for Rossetti's Rachel which will allow him to buy Rossetti's Francesca. Ruskin admits that Rossetti had offered to sell him the Francesca at a lower price but Ruskin insisted that he and Heaton be offered the same price. Ruskin has sent Heaton some works by Turner to answer her question "about Turner's trees." He tells Heaton that when she returns Rossetti's Francesca, she should send it to him, not Rossetti. He tells her that Paolo and Francesca should have been depicted as walking through hail, not fire, but that Rossetti "did'nt [sic] know how to do hail." [Date provided by Surtees: Latter part of November 1855]
    Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's vision of Rachel and Leah; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Paolo and Francesca da Rimini; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 late November; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.25)
    Ruskin asks Heaton if she could arrange for a photographer to go to Bolton and take a photograph of the scene depicted in Turner's Bolton Abbey, and to collect bits of rock from the area. Ruskin praises both Arthur Hughes's painting and Robert Browning's recently published poem "An Epistle Containing the Strange Medical Experience of Karshish the Arab Physician", expressing his surprise that he should agree with the Athenaeum 's review of the text. In a postscript, Ruskin makes a sketch depicting the size of the rocks he wants to be collected from Bolton and remarks that Dante's Leah and Rachel are the "action" of life and that he has dedicated an entire chapter to them in his forthcoming book ( Modern Painters III ). [Date provided by Surtees: Late November 1855]
    Photography; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900. Modern painters; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's vision of Rachel and Leah; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Bolton Abbey; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Hughes, Arthur, 1832-1915; Browning, Robert, 1812-1889; Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321; Bolton Abbey (Bolton Abbey, England); Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 November 29; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.26)
    Ruskin tells Heaton he received the Bolton Abbey photograph and rocks safely. Ruskin asks Heaton if she could arrange to have another photograph taken of the area, at the back of the river. Ruskin tells Heaton that the chapter on Leah and Rachel he referred to in his previous letter relates to Dante's, not Rossetti's, work. In a postscript, Ruskin asks Heaton to pass on his admiration to J. W. Ramsden, the photographer of the Bolton Abbey scene.
    Bolton Abbey (Bolton Abbey, England); Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321; Ramsden, John William; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 December; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.27)
    Ruskin admits that time constraints mean that his letter is late and "hastily" written. He asks Heaton about the positioning of the proofs of the latest Bolton Abbey photographs and enquires after a bridge, mentioned in Heaton's last letter to him, which has apparently been built since Ruskin's last visit to the area. Ruskin asks Heaton to arrange for another two photographs to be taken, with a view from Holme Terrace. Ruskin says Heaton can return Rossetti's Francesca with the photographs but that there is no rush. [Date provided by Surtees: December 1855]
    Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Paolo and Francesca da Rimini; Bolton Abbey (Bolton Abbey, England); Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 December 23; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.28)
    Ruskin stresses that he is not ungrateful for Heaton's help and wishes her a merry Christmas. He explains that he cannot give Heaton the reasons for his commissioning of the Bolton photographs because it is related to the fourth volume of Modern Painters, which will not be published for at least two months. Ruskin encourages Heaton to contemplate "Dante's riddle about Rachel and Matilda" and gives her hints about how she might "make it out." Ruskin recommends H.F. Cary's translation of Dante over that of C.B. Cayley. Ruskin says that he is delighted that Heaton's friends like Rossetti's Francesca and that Rossetti and that Rossetti will be too. Ruskin gives further instructions regarding the photographing of Bolton Abbey. [Date provided by Surtees: 23 December 1855]
    Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Paolo and Francesca da Rimini; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Bolton Abbey (Bolton Abbey, England); Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1855 December 30; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (2 pages): autograph letter; 32 x 20 cm (Box 1, Folder H.29)
    Ruskin wishes Heaton a happy new year. Ruskin gives further hints to Heaton about "Dante's riddle,", expanding on the idea that Beatrice and Matilda represent the "Active and Contemplative faculties" and musing upon Dante's meaning. Ruskin tells Heaton that Rossetti's Francesca arrived with him safely and that he is glad that the work was well-received in Heaton's circle. Ruskin tells Heaton that she cannot yet commission any work from Elizabeth Siddall, who is too ill to draw. Ruskin has assisted Siddall to go to Nice for the winter and hopes that she will paint some works of the "blue sea & orange groves" for him. Ruskin asks Heaton to allow him to mentor Siddall further before purchasing any of her work and instead encourages Heaton to commission work from one of his pupils who, for financial reasons, is unable to work full-time as an artist. Ruskin apologizes for using foolscap for his letter instead of notepaper, admitting it is easier for him to write on the former. Ruskin sends his best wishes for the new year.
    Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Paolo and Francesca da Rimini; Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Siddall, Elizabeth; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 January; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (2 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.30)
    Ruskin apologizes for not sending Heaton a copy of his newly published Modern Painters III but says he will pay for Heaton's order of a drawing from "the workman" (presumably the artist mentioned in his previous letter) and will autograph Heaton's copy of his book the next time she comes to town. Ruskin expresses his happiness that Heaton enjoyed the book and tells her that the "best plate" in the work is his etching of Bolton which contains more "than appears at first." Ruskin says that he is unwell and so cannot write very much presently. [Date provided by Surtees: 23 January 1856]
    Ruskin, John, 1819-1900. Modern painters; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 February?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.31)
    "I hope I am in time to say -- by all means let R's [Rossetti's] picture be seen at Literary Society. I send you a silver and black frame for it -- the one I had it in. It looks well in it. Always faithfully Yrs" [Date provided by Surtees: ? February 1856]
    Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Leeds Philosophical and Literary Society; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 late February?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.32)
    Ruskin asks Heaton to inform him if she receives his letter as he wants to be sure she will not allow "the pictures" to be seen. Ruskin makes arrangements to have the Rossetti works recently purchased by Heaton displayed for exhibition, explaining all correspondence relating to the matter should be address to Rossetti. Ruskin tells Heaton that he has recently recovered from a two-week bout of illness which has thrown him "much into arrear.". In a postscript, Ruskin describes some vignettes he has viewed as "both very bad" and tells Heaton that "the Bacharach you liked" and Turner's Corinth from the Acropolis are both good but not equal to Heaton's vignettes. [Date provided by Surtees: ? Latter half of February 1856]
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Bacharach on the Rhine; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Corinth from the Acropolis; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 early March; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (2 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.33)
    Ruskin tells Heaton that Rossetti has received both of the works she sent for the exhibition. Ruskin reiterates that all correspondence relating to the exhibition should be addressed to Rossetti. Ruskin asks Heaton how much she would be willing to pay for a work by Turner, telling her it is likely to be between £180 to £200 and enquires whether he should secure a good work by Turner as soon as he finds one. [Date provided by Surtees: Early March 1856]
    Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 April 12; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (2 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.34)
    Ruskin tells Heaton that he will be frank with her with regards to what he would like her to do so that Heaton can assist him, if she is able to. Ruskin is going to Oxford and describes his transportation method ("a fly & a single horse"). Ruskin agrees with Heaton that "Ida" (Elizabeth Siddall) should go to Switzerland for the summer.
    Siddall, Elizabeth; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 early May; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter; 32 x 21 cm (Box 1, Folder H.36)
    Memorandum detailing Ruskin's debt to Heaton for items such as the Bolton Abbey photographs and Heaton's debt to Ruskin for her photographs and pieces from Turner's Liber Studiorum. [Date provided by Surtees: May 1856]
    Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851. Liber Studiorum; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 October 6; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.37)
    "I quite forgot to tell you I was now going to read your tales carefully ... the tales are pretty & amusing. I like them much but there is a weakness in the style I must try to explain to you." In a postscript: "I have written to Oxford for the drawings. Love to Mr Richmond.". [Date provided by Surtees: Monday 6th October 1856]
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 October 7; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.38)
    Ruskin tells Heaton he will be glad for the loan of her Rossetti watercolor Dante's Dream after the Brownings (to whom Heaton was currently loaning the work) leave for Florence. Ruskin asks to borrow Turner's Castle St Angelo from Heaton as "there is more in these vignettes than I thought." Ruskin tells Heaton that, inspired by Heaton, he has bought two Turner vignettes. Ruskin debates the benefits of exhibiting at the Colnaghi gallery. Ruskin informs Heaton he might ask for her financial support for his "men who are to learn to engrave Turner.". Ruskin tells Heaton he will be happy to show her the works by Elizabeth Siddall in his possession and suggests a time she might visit him to view them. [Date given by postmark: 7 October 1856]
    Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Turner, J. M. W. (Joseph Mallord William), 1775-1851; Siddall, Elizabeth; P. & D. Colnaghi & Co.; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 October 12; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.39)
    Ruskin tells Heaton he will not be able to meet her as planned as two friends are visiting him from Northumberland and so promises to send Heaton the Elizabeth Siddall drawings. Ruskin says he believes the "Rossetti drawing is in town" but tells Heaton he will confirm if it is when he sends the Siddall works. In a postscript, Ruskin praises Byron's "Destruction of Sennacherib" which appeared in the Oxford and Cambridge Magazine No. 8, exclaiming: "That profound last stanza -- the infinite power and ease of all!!!" [Date provided by Surtees: Sunday 12th October 1856]
    Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Siddall, Elizabeth; Byron, George Gordon Byron, Baron, 1788-1824; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 October 13; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm (Box 1, Folder H.40)
    "Sadly crushed in my pocket -- the enclosed is nevertheless worth making out as you will see how R. [Rossetti] feels himself about the drawing. I have sent word to [Arthur] Hughes to send it to you instantly -- as I can't go & see it -- if there is anything shocking in it -- it is not my fault." [Date provided by Surtees: Monday 13th October 1856]
    Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; Hughes, Arthur, 1832-1915; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900 -- Correspondence
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 October 14?; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.41)
    "All kinds of people -- old friends, and stiff unreformable new ones -- have written to say they are coming here tomorrow, Wednesday -- our day for Miss Siddall -- Can you make it Thursday at 12 instead -- or if not Friday -- I am afraid I could not get a minutes [sic] time tomorrow." [Date provided by Surtees: 14th? October 1856]
  - John Ruskin letter to Ellen Heaton, 1856 October or November; 1 sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder H.42)
    Ruskin tells Heaton he hadn't seen her previous letter when he met her in church, as he had been in Slough. Ruskin admits to Heaton that he hadn't told her about a number of Turner works because he thought them overpriced. He describes Turner's Rhine works as "toppers" but says they are too expensive and advises Heaton to buy Alnwick Castle or Aldorough. He describes only the sky of Turner's Folkestone from the Sea as good but praises the sky itself highly. Ruskin declares Alnwick Castle the best of the four but Alborough as having more value for money. Ruskin admits he would like Heaton to acquire as many Turner works as possible as he wants "them to be more in my power". Ruskin says when he visits Heaton he will take "the Dante" under his "charge.". [Date provided by Surtees: October - November 1856]